<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Dream Story</title>
        <title type="alt">Traumnovelle</title>
        <title type="alt">Rhapsody: A Dream Novel</title>
        <editor role="Translator">Otto P. Schinnerer</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent>
        <measure unit="pages" quantity="143">143 pages</measure>
      </extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Green Integer</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Los Angeles</pubPlace>
        <idno type="ISBN-10">1931243484</idno>
        <idno type="ISBN-13">9781931243483</idno>
        <date>2003</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="s">Masterworks of fiction</title>
        <biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note><!-- notes on other aspects of the resource -->
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p><!-- information about the source from which the resource was derived  -->
        </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <particDesc>
      <listPerson>
        <rs type="person" >
          <rs type="person" xml:id="Fridolin">Fridolin</rs>
          <age>30s</age>
          <description>rugged</description>
        </rs>
        <rs type="person" >
          <rs type="person" xml:id="Albertina">Albertina</rs>
        </rs>
        <rs type="person" >
          <rs type="person" xml:id="STRANGER">A stranger</rs>
          <description>blase manner, apparently Polish accent</description>
        </rs>
        <rs type="person" >
          <rs type="person" xml:id="2W">Two women in red dominoes</rs>
        </rs>
      </listPerson>
      <listEvent>
        <event>
          <eventDesc xml:id="MASQ">masquerade ball</eventDesc>
        </event>
        <event>
          <eventDesc xml:id="CARNIVAL">carnival period</eventDesc>
        </event>
      </listEvent>
      <listPlace>
        <place>
          <placeName xml:id="Denmark">Denmark</placeName>
        </place>
        <place>
          <placeName xml:id="ball-room">ball-room</placeName>
        </place>
      </listPlace>
    </particDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart>RHAPSODY A DREAM NOVEL</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>Arthur Schnitzler</docAuthor> Translated from the German by OTTO P. SCHINNERER
        </byline>
      </titlePage>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="chapter" n="1">
        <head>1.</head>
        <p>
          <quote>"TWENTY-FOUR brown-skinned slaves rowed the splendid gallery which was to bring
          Prince Amgiad to the palace of the caliph. The Prince, wrapped in his purple cloak, lay
          alone on the deck
            under the dark-blue, starry sky, and his gaze—"</quote><lb /> So far the little girl had
          read aloud.Then, suddenly, her eyelids drooped. Her parents looked at each other and
          smiled. <rs type="person" ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> bent down, kissed her blond hair
          and closed the book which was lying on the untidy table. The child looked up as if caught
          at some mischief.<lb />
            <said aloud="true" direct="true">"It's nine o'clock,"</said> her
          father said, <said aloud="true" direct="true">"and time you were in bed."</said> <rs
            ref="#Albertina">Albertina</rs>also bent over her, and as her hand met her husband's on
          the beloved forehead, they looked at each other with a tender smile not meant for the
          child. The governess entered and asked the little girl to say good-night. She got up
          obediently, kissed her father and mother and walked out quietly hand in hand with the
          young woman. <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="#Albertina">
            Albertina</rs>, left alone under the reddish glow of the hanging-lamp, continued the
          conversation they had begun before supper. </p>

        <p> It dealt with their experiences the night before at the <eventName ref="#MASQ">masquerade
          ball</eventName>. They had decided to attend it just before the end of the <eventName
            ref="#CARNIVAL">carnival period</eventName>, as their first one of the season. No sooner
          had <rs type="person" ref="Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> entered the ball-room than he was
          greeted, like a long lost friend, by <rs type="person" ref="#2W">two
            women</rs> in red dominoes. <rs type="person" ref="#Fridolin">He</rs> had no idea who
          they were, although they were unusually well-informed about many affairs of his student
          days and internship. They had invited him into a box with great friendliness, but had left
          again with the promise that they would soon return without masks. When they did not
          appear, he became impatient and went down to the ball-room floor hoping to meet them
          again, but eagerly as he scanned the room, he could not see them anywhere. Instead,
          however, another woman unexpectedly took his arm. It was his <rs type="person"
            ref="#Albertina">wife</rs>. She had just freed herself from the company of a <rs
            type="person"
            ref="#STRANGER">stranger</rs> whose blase manner and apparently Polish accent had at
          first charmed her. Suddenly he had offended her--frightened her by a rather common and
          impertinent remark. <rs type="person" ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> and <rs
            ref="#Albertina">Albertina</rs> were glad to have escaped from a disappointingly
          commonplace masquerade prank, and soon sat like two lovers, among the other couples, in
          the buffet, eating oysters and drinking champagne. They chatted gaily, as though they had
          just made each other's acquaintance, acting a comedy of courting, bashful resistance,
          seduction and surrender. After driving home quickly through the snowy winter night, they
          sank into each other's arms and were more blissful in their ardent love than they had been
          for a long time. The gray of morning awakened them only too soon. Fridolin's profession
          summoned him to his patients at an early hour, while <rs type="person" ref="#Albertina">
          Albertina</rs> would not stay in bed longer because of her duties as housewife and mother.
          So the ensuing hours passed, soberly and predetermined, in daily routine and work, and the
          events of the night before, both those at the beginning and at the end, had faded. </p>

        <p> But now that the day's work was done— the child had gone to bed and no disturbance was
          likely—the shadowy forms of the masquerade, the melancholy stranger and the red dominoes,
          rose again into reality. And all at once those insignificant events were imbued, magically
          and painfully, with the deceptive glow of neglected opportunities. Harmless but probing
          questions, and sly, ambiguous answers were exchanged. Neither failed to notice
          that the other was not absolutely honest, and so they became slightly vindictive. They
          exaggerated the degree of attraction that their unknown partners at the ball had exerted
          upon them while each made fun of the other's tendencies to jealousy and denied his own.
          Soon, their light conversation about the trifling matters of the night before changed into
          a more serious discussion of those hidden, scarcely suspected wishes, which can produce
          dangerous whirlpools even in the serenest and purest soul. They spoke of those mysterious
          regions of which they were hardly conscious but toward which the incomprehensible wind of
          fate might some day drive them, even if only in their dreams. For though they were united
          in thought and feeling, they knew that the preceding day had not been the first time that
          the spirit of adventure, freedom and danger had beckoned them. Uneasy, and tormenting
          themselves, each sought with disingenuous curiosity to draw out confessions from the
          other. Anxiously, they searched within themselves for some indifferent fact, or trifling
          experience, which might express the inexpressible, and the honest confession of which
          might relieve them of the strain and the suspicion which were becoming unbearable. </p>

        <p> Whether <rs type="person" ref="#Albertina">Albertina</rs> was more impatient, more
          honest or more kind-hearted of the two, it was she who first summoned the courage for a
          frank confession. She asked <rs type="person" ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> in a rather
          uncertain voice whether he remembered the young man who—last summer at the seashore in
          Denmark—had been sitting one evening with two other officers at an adjoining table. He had
          received a telegram during dinner, whereupon he had hastily said "good-bye" to his
          friends.</p>
        <p>
          <rs type="person" ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> nodded. <said aloud="true" direct="true">"What
          about him?"</said> he asked. </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
