<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Dream Story</title>
        <title type="alt">Traumnovelle</title>
        <title type="alt">Rhapsody: A Dream Novel</title>
        <editor role="Translator">Otto P. Schinnerer</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent>
        <measure unit="pages" quantity="143">143 pages</measure>
      </extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Green Integer</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Los Angeles</pubPlace>
        <idno type="ISBN-10">1931243484</idno>
        <idno type="ISBN-13">9781931243483</idno>
        <date>2003</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="s">Masterworks of fiction</title>
        <biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note><!-- notes on other aspects of the resource -->
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p><!-- information about the source from which the resource was derived  -->
        </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <rs type="person">
            <rs type="person" xml:id="Fridolin">Fridolin</rs>
            <age>30s</age>
            <description> doctor, rugged, knows how to play piano</description>
          </rs>
          <rs type="person">
            <rs type="person" xml:id="Albertina">Albertina</rs>
          </rs>
          <rs type="person">
            <rs type="person" xml:id="STRANGER">A stranger</rs>
            <description>blase manner, apparently Polish accent</description>
          </rs>
          <rs type="person">
            <rs type="person" xml:id="2W">Two women in red dominoes</rs>
          </rs>
          <rs type="person">
            <rs type="person" xml:id="daughter">Fridolin and Albertina's daughter</rs>
            <description>blonde hair</description>
          </rs>
          <rs type="person">
            <rs type="person" xml:id="governess">Governess</rs>
          </rs>
          <rs type="person">
            <rs type="person" xml:id="younggirl">Young girl</rs>
          </rs>
          <rs type="person">
            <rs type="person" xml:id="councilor">councilor</rs>
          </rs>
          <rs type="person">
            <rs type="person" xml:id="Marianne">Marianne</rs>
            <description>Councilor's daughter, was blond and thick, but dry; her neck well-formed
              and
              slender, although a little wrinkled
              and rather yellow; and her lips were thin and firmly pressed together.</description>
          </rs>
          <rs type="person">
            <rs type="person" xml:id="Roediger">Doctor Roediger</rs>
            <description>Marianne's fiance.</description>
          </rs>
          <rs type="person">
            <rs type="person" xml:id="Mizzi">Mizzi</rs>
          </rs>
          <rs type="person">
            <rs type="person" xml:id="Nachtigall">Nachtigall</rs>
            <description>young
              man, Jew, tall, rather broad, and none too thin. His long, blond, slightly curly hair
              had a
              touch of gray in it, and his moustache drooped in Polish fashion. He was wearing an
              open
              gray top-coat, underneath which were visible a greasy dress-suit, a crumpled shirt
              with
              three false diamond studs, a crinkled collar and a dangling, white silk tie. His
              eyelids
              were inflamed, as if from many sleepless nights, but his blue eyes gleamed brightly.</description>
          </rs>
        </listPerson>
        <listEvent>
          <event>
            <eventDesc xml:id="MASQ">masquerade ball</eventDesc>
          </event>
          <event>
            <eventDesc xml:id="CARNIVAL">carnival period</eventDesc>
          </event>
        </listEvent>
        <listPlace>
          <place xml:id="Denmark" type="country">
            <placeName>Denmark</placeName>
          </place>
          <place>
            <placeName xml:id="ball-room">ball-room</placeName>
          </place>
          <place>
            <placeName xml:id="worther">Lake Worther</placeName>
          </place>
          <place>
            <placeName xml:id="schrey">Schreyvogel Strasse</placeName>
          </place>
          <place>
            <placeName xml:id="hospital">General Hospital</placeName>
          </place>
          <place>
            <placeName xml:id="park">Rathaus Park</placeName>
          </place>
          <place xml:id="Vienna" type="city">
            <placeName>Vienna</placeName>
            <location>
              <country>Austria</country>
              <geo>48.210033 16.363449</geo>
            </location>
          </place>
          <place>
            <placeName xml:id="square">Rathaus Square</placeName>
          </place>
          <place>
            <placeName xml:id="schonbrunn">Schonbrunn Strasse</placeName>
          </place>
          <place>
            <placeName xml:id="hotel">Riedhof Hotel</placeName>
          </place>
        </listPlace>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart>RHAPSODY A DREAM NOVEL</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>Arthur Schnitzler</docAuthor> Translated from the German by OTTO P. SCHINNERER </byline>
      </titlePage>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="chapter" n="1">
        <head>1.</head>
        <p>
          <quote>"TWENTY-FOUR brown-skinned slaves rowed the splendid gallery which was to bring
          Prince Amgiad to the palace of the caliph. The Prince, wrapped in his purple cloak, lay
          alone on the deck
            under the dark-blue, starry sky, and his gaze—"</quote><lb /> So far the <rs
            ref="#daughter">little girl</rs> had read aloud.Then, suddenly, her eyelids drooped. Her
          parents looked at each other and smiled. <rs type="person" ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs>
          bent down, kissed her blond hair and closed the book which was lying on the untidy table.
          The child looked up as if caught at some mischief.<lb />
            <said aloud="true" direct="true"
            who="Fridolin" listener="daughter">"It's nine o'clock,"</said> her father said, <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="daughter">"and time you were in
            bed."</said> <rs
            ref="#Albertina">Albertina</rs>also bent over her, and as her hand met her husband's on
          the beloved forehead, they looked at each other with a tender smile not meant for the
          child. The <rs ref="#governess">governess</rs> entered and asked the little girl to say
          good-night. She got up obediently, kissed her father and mother and walked out quietly
          hand in hand with the young woman. <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="#Albertina">
            Albertina</rs>, left alone under the reddish glow of the hanging-lamp, continued the
          conversation they had begun before supper. </p>

        <p> It dealt with their experiences the night before at the <eventName ref="#MASQ">masquerade
          ball</eventName>. They had decided to attend it just before the end of the <eventName
            ref="#CARNIVAL">carnival period</eventName>, as their first one of the season. No sooner
          had <rs type="person" ref="Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> entered the ball-room than he was
          greeted, like a long lost friend, by <rs type="person" ref="#2W">two
            women</rs> in red dominoes. <rs type="person" ref="#Fridolin">He</rs> had no idea who
          they were, although they were unusually well-informed about many affairs of his student
          days and internship. They had invited him into a box with great friendliness, but had left
          again with the promise that they would soon return without masks. When they did not
          appear, he became impatient and went down to the ball-room floor hoping to meet them
          again, but eagerly as he scanned the room, he could not see them anywhere. Instead,
          however, another woman unexpectedly took his arm. It was his <rs type="person"
            ref="#Albertina">wife</rs>. She had just freed herself from the company of a <rs
            type="person"
            ref="#STRANGER">stranger</rs> whose blase manner and apparently Polish accent had at
          first charmed her. Suddenly he had offended her--frightened her by a rather common and
          impertinent remark. <rs type="person" ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> and <rs
            ref="#Albertina">Albertina</rs> were glad to have escaped from a disappointingly
          commonplace masquerade prank, and soon sat like two lovers, among the other couples, in
          the buffet, eating oysters and drinking champagne. They chatted gaily, as though they had
          just made each other's acquaintance, acting a comedy of courting, bashful resistance,
          seduction and surrender. After driving home quickly through the snowy winter night, they
          sank into each other's arms and were more blissful in their ardent love than they had been
          for a long time. The gray of morning awakened them only too soon. Fridolin's profession
          summoned him to his patients at an early hour, while <rs type="person" ref="#Albertina">
          Albertina</rs> would not stay in bed longer because of her duties as housewife and mother.
          So the ensuing hours passed, soberly and predetermined, in daily routine and work, and the
          events of the night before, both those at the beginning and at the end, had faded. </p>

        <p>
          But now that the day's work was done— the child had gone to bed and no disturbance was
          likely—the shadowy forms of the masquerade, the melancholy stranger and the red dominoes,
          rose again into reality. And all at once those insignificant events were imbued, magically
          and painfully, with the deceptive glow of neglected opportunities. Harmless but probing
          questions, and sly, ambiguous answers were exchanged. Neither failed to notice
          that the other was not absolutely honest, and so they became slightly vindictive. They
          exaggerated the degree of attraction that their unknown partners at the ball had exerted
          upon them while each made fun of the other's tendencies to jealousy and denied his own.
          Soon, their light conversation about the trifling matters of the night before changed into
          a more serious discussion of those hidden, scarcely suspected wishes, which can produce
          dangerous whirlpools even in the serenest and purest soul. They spoke of those mysterious
          regions of which they were hardly conscious but toward which the incomprehensible wind of
          fate might some day drive them, even if only in their dreams. For though they were united
          in thought and feeling, they knew that the preceding day had not been the first time that
          the spirit of adventure, freedom and danger had beckoned them. Uneasy, and tormenting
          themselves, each sought with disingenuous curiosity to draw out confessions from the
          other. Anxiously, they searched within themselves for some indifferent fact, or trifling
          experience, which might express the inexpressible, and the honest confession of which
          might relieve them of the strain and the suspicion which were becoming unbearable. </p>

        <p> Whether <rs type="person" ref="#Albertina">Albertina</rs> was more impatient, more
          honest or more kind-hearted of the two, it was she who first summoned the courage for a
          frank confession. She asked <rs type="person" ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> in a rather
          uncertain voice whether he remembered the young man who—last summer at the seashore in
          Denmark—had been sitting one evening with two other officers at an adjoining table. He had
          received a telegram during dinner, whereupon he had hastily said "good-bye" to his
          friends.</p>
        <p>
          <rs type="person" ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> nodded. <said aloud="true" direct="true"
            who="Fridolin" listener="Albertina">"What
            about him?"</said> he asked. </p>
        <p>
          <said aloud="true" direct="true" who="Albertina" listener="Fridolin">I'd already seen him
          in the morning,"</said> she replied, <said aloud="true" direct="true" who="Albertina"
            listener="Fridolin">"as he was hurrying up the stairs in the hotel with
            his yellow hand-bag. He looked at me as he passed, but didn't stop until he had gone a
          few more steps.
            Then he turned and our eyes met. He didn't smile; in fact, it seemed to me that he
          scowled. I suppose I
            did the same, for I was very much stirred. That whole day I lay on the beach, lost in
          dreams. Had he
            called me—I thought—I could not have resisted. I thought I was ready for anything. I had
          practically
            resolved to give up you, the child, my future, and at the same time —if you can
          understand it?—you
            were dearer to me than ever. That same afternoon—surely you remember—we discussed many
          things
            very intimately, among others our common future, and our child. At sunset you and I were
          sitting on the
            balcony, when, down below on the beach, he passed without looking up. I was extremely
          thrilled to see
            him, but I stroked your forehead and kissed your hair, and my love for you was both
          sorrowful and
            compassionate. That evening at dinner I wore a white rose and you yourself said I was
          very beautiful.
            Perhaps it wasn't mere chance that the stranger and his friends sat near us. He didn't
          look at me, but I
            considered getting up, walking over to him and saying: Here I am, my beloved for whom I
          have waited —
            take me. At that moment the telegram was handed to him. He read it, turned pale,
          whispered a few
            words to the younger of the two officers—and glancing at me mysteriously he left the
          room."</said>
        </p>

        <p>
          <said aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Albertina">"And then?"</said>
          <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> asked dryly when she stopped. </p>
        <p>
          <said aloud="true" direct="true" who="Albertina" listener="Fridolin">"That is all. I
            remember that I woke the next morning with a restless anxiety. I don't know whether I
            was afraid that he had left or that he might still be there. But when he didn't appear
            at noon, I breathed a sigh of relief. Don't ask any more, <rs ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs>.
            I've told you the whole truth. And you, too, had some sort of experience at the
            seashore—I know it."</said>
        </p>

        <p>
          <rs ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> rose, walked up and down the room several times and then
          said: <said aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Albertina">"You're right."</said>
          He was standing at the window, his face in shadow and in a hoarse and slightly hostile
          voice he began: <said aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Albertina">In
          the morning, sometimes very early before you got up, I used to stroll along the beach, out
          beyond the town. Even at that hour the sun was always shining over the sea, bright and
          strong. Out there on the beach, as you know, were cottages, each one standing like a world
          in itself. Some had fenced-in gardens, others were surrounded only by the woods. The
          bathing-huts were separated from the cottages by the road and part of the beach. I hardly
          ever met people at such an early hour, and bathers were never out. One morning, quite
          suddenly, I noticed the figure of a woman. She had suddenly appeared on the narrow ledge
          of a bathing-hut, which rested on piles driven into the sand. She was cautiously
          advancing, placing one foot before the other, her arms extended backward against the
          wooden boards. She was quite a <rs ref="#younggirl">young girl</rs>, possibly fifteen
          years old, with loose blond hair hanging over her shoulders and on one side over her
          delicate breast. She was looking down into the water and was slowly moving along the wall,
          her gaze lowered in the direction of the far corner. All at once she stopped opposite me
          and reached far back with her arms as though trying to secure a firmer hold. Looking up,
          she suddenly saw me. A tremor passed through her body, as though she wished to drop into
          the water or run. But as she could move only very slowly on the narrow ledge, she had to
          stay where she was. She stood there with a face expressing at first fright, then anger,
          and finally embarrassment. All at once, however, she smiled, smiled marvelously. Her eyes
          welcomed me, beckoned to me, and at the same time slightly mocked me, as she glanced at
          the strip of water between us. Then she stretched her young and slender body, glad of her
          beauty, and proudly and sweetly stirred by my obvious admiration. We stood facing each
          other for perhaps ten seconds, with half-open lips and dazzled eyes. Involuntarily I
          stretched out my arms to her; her eyes expressed surrender and joy. Then she shook her
          head vigorously, took one arm from the wall and commanded me with a gesture to go away.
          When I didn't at once obey, her childlike eyes turned on me such a beseeching look that
          there was nothing for me to do but to go, and I went as quickly as possible. I did not
          look back once—not because I felt considerate, obedient or chivalrous, but because in her
          last glance I sensed an emotion so intense, so far beyond anything I had ever experienced,
          that I was not far from fainting."</said> And he stopped. </p>
        <p> With her eyes cast down and in a monotonous voice, <rs ref="#Albertina">
            Albertina</rs> asked: <said aloud="true" direct="true" who="Albertina"
            listener="Fridolin">And
            how often
            did you
            see her
            after that?"</said>
        </p>
        <p>
          <said aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Albertina">"What I have told
          you,"</said> <rs ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> answered, <said aloud="true" direct="true"
            who="Fridolin" listener="Albertina">"happened on the last day of our stay in Denmark.
          Otherwise I don't know what might have taken place. You, too, mustn't ask any more, <rs
              ref="#Albertina">Albertina</rs>."</said>
        </p>
        <p> He was still standing at the window, motionless as <rs
            ref="#Albertina">Albertina</rs> arose and walked over to him. There were tears in her
          eyes and a slight frown on her face. <said aloud="true" direct="true" who="Albertina"
            listener="Fridolin">"In the future let's always tell each other such
            things at once,"</said> she said. </p>
        <p>He nodded in silence. <said aloud="true" direct="true" who="Albertina"
            listener="Fridolin">"Will you promise me?"</said>
        </p>
        <p> He took her into his arms. <said aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin"
            listener="Albertina">"Don't
            you know that?"</said> he asked. But his voice was still harsh. </p>
        <p>She took his hands and looked up at him with misty eyes, in the depths of which he could
          read her thoughts. She was thinking of his other and more real experiences, those of his
          young manhood, many of which she knew about. When they were first married he had yielded,
          all too readily, to her jealous curiosity and had told her (indeed it often seemed to him)
          had surrendered to her many secrets which he should rather have kept to himself. He knew
          that she was inevitably reminded of these affairs and he was hardly surprised when she
          murmured the half-forgotten name of one of his early sweethearts. It sounded to him a
          little like a reproach, or was it a covert threat?
        </p>
        <p> He raised her hands to his lips. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Albertina">"You may believe me, even
          though it sounds trite, that in every woman I thought I loved it was always you I was
          looking for—I know that better than you can understand it, <rs ref="#Albertina">Albertina</rs>
          ." </said>
        </p>
        <p>A dispirited smile passed over her face. <said aloud="true" direct="true"
            who="Albertina" listener="Fridolin">"And suppose before meeting you, I, too, had gone on
          a search for a
            mate?"</said> she asked. The look in her eyes changed, becoming cool and impenetrable,
          and he allowed her hands to slip from his, as though he had caught her lying or committing
          a breach of faith. She, however, continued: <said aloud="true" direct="true"
            who="Albertina" listener="Fridolin">"Oh, if you men knew!"</said> and again was silent. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Albertina">"If we
            knew—? What do you mean by that?"</said> In a strangely harsh voice she replied: <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Albertina" listener="Fridolin">"About what you imagine,
          my dear."</said> <said aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Albertina">"<rs
              ref="#Albertina">Albertina</rs>!—then there is something that you've kept from me?"</said>
          She nodded, and looked down with a strange smile. Incomprehensible, monstrous doubts
          crossed his mind. <said aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Albertina">"I
          don't quite understand,"</said> he said. <said aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin"
            listener="Albertina">"You were barely seventeen when we became engaged."</said><said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Albertina" listener="Fridolin">"Past sixteen, yes, <rs
              ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs>. But it wasn't my fault that I was a virgin when I
          became your wife."</said> She looked at him brightly. <said aloud="true" direct="true"
            who="Fridolin" listener="Albertina">"<rs ref="#Albertina">Albertina</rs>——!"</said> But
          she continued: <said aloud="true" direct="true" who="Albertina" listener="Fridolin">"It
            was a beautiful summer evening at Lake Worther, just before our engagement, and a very
          handsome young man stood before my window that overlooked a large and spacious meadow. As
          we talked I thought to myself—just listen to this—what a charming young man that is—he
          would only have to say the word—it would have to be the right one, certainly—and I would
            go out with him into the meadow or the woods—or it would be even more beautiful in a
            boat
            on the lake—and I would grant him this night anything he might desire. That is what I
          thought to myself.—But he didn't say a word, that charming young man. He only kissed my
          hand tenderly— and next morning he asked me—if I would be his wife. And I said yes."</said>
        </p>
        <p>
          <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> was annoyed and dropped her hand. <said aloud="true"
            direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Albertina">"And if,"</said> he said, <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Albertina">"someone else had stood
            by your window that night and the right word had occurred to him, if it had been, for
          instance—"</said> He was considering, but she raised her hand protestingly. </p>
        <p><said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Albertina">"Any other man—no
            matter who—could have said anything he liked—it would have been useless. And if it
            hadn't
            been you standing by the window, then very likely the summer evening wouldn't have been
          so
            beautiful."</said> And she smiled at him. </p>
        <p> There was a scornful expression about his mouth. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Albertina">"Yes,
            that's what you say now. Perhaps you even believe it at this moment. But——"</said>
        </p>
        <p>There was a knock on the door. The maid entered and said that the housekeeper from
          Schreyvogel Strasse had come to fetch the doctor, as the Privy Councilor was very low
          again. <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">
            Fridolin</rs> went out into the hall, and when the woman told him that the Councilor had
          had a very serious heart attack, he promised to come at once. As he was leaving, <rs
            ref="#Albertina">Albertina</rs> asked: <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Albertina" listener="Fridolin">"You're going away?"</said>
          She said it with as much annoyance as if he were deliberately doing her an injustice. <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> replied, with astonishment: <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Albertina">"I suppose I've got to."</said>
          She sighed regretfully. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Albertina">"I hope it
            won't be very serious,"</said> said <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs>. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Albertina">"Up to now three
          centigrams
            of morphine have always
            pulled him through."</said> The maid brought his fur coat, and absent-mindedly kissing <rs
            ref="#Albertina">Albertina</rs> on her forehead and mouth, as if everything during the
          last hour had been completely forgotten, he hurried away. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" n="2">
        <head>2.</head>
        <p>WHEN <rs ref="#Fridolin">
            Fridolin</rs> reached the street, he unbuttoned his coat. It had suddenly begun to thaw;
          the snow on the sidewalk was almost gone, and there was a touch of spring in the air. It
          was less than a quarter of an hour's walk to Schreyvogel Strasse from his home near the
          General Hospital, and he soon reached the old house. He walked up the dimly lighted
          winding staircase to the second floor and pulled the bell-rope. But before the
          old-fashioned bell was heard, he noticed that the door was ajar, and entering through the
          unlighted foyer into the living room he saw at once that he had come too late. The
          green-shaded kerosene lamp which was hanging from the low ceiling cast a dim light on the
          bedspread under which a lean body lay motionless. <rs ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> knew
          the old man so well that he seemed to see the face plainly, although it was outside the
          circle of light— the high forehead, the thin and lined cheeks, the snow-white beard and
          also the strikingly ugly ears with coarse, white hairs. At the foot of the bed sat <rs
            ref="#Marianne">Marianne</rs>, the Councilor's daughter, completely exhausted, her arms
          hanging limply from her shoulders. An odor of old furniture, medicine, petroleum and
          cooking pervaded the room, and in addition to that there was a trace of eau de Cologne and
          scented soap. <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> also noticed the indefinite, sweetish scent of this pale
          girl who was still young and who had been slowly fading for months and years under the
          stress of severe household duties, nursing and night watches. When the doctor entered she
          looked up, but because of the dim light he could not see whether she had blushed, as
          usual, when he appeared. She started to rise, but he stopped her with a movement of his
          hand, and so she merely greeted him with a nod, her eyes large and sad. He stepped to the
          head of the bed and mechanically placed his hands on the forehead of the dead man and on
          the arms which were lying on the bed-spread in loose and open shirt sleeves. His shoulders
          drooped with a slight expression of regret. He stuck his hands into the pockets of his
          coat and his eyes wandered about the room until they finally rested on <rs ref="#Marianne">
          Marianne</rs>. Her hair was blond and thick, but dry; her neck well-formed and slender,
          although a little wrinkled and rather yellow; and her lips were thin and firmly pressed
          together. <said aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Marianne">Well, my
          dear <rs ref="#Marianne">Marianne</rs>,"</said> he said in a slightly embarrassed whisper, <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Marianne">"you weren't entirely
          unprepared for
            this."</said> She held out her hand to him. He took it sympathetically and inquired
          about the particulars of the final, fatal attack. <said aloud="true" direct="false"
            who="Marianne" listener="Fridolin">She reported briefly and to the point, and then spoke
          of her father's last comparatively easy days, during which <rs ref="#Fridolin">
              Fridolin</rs> had not seen him.</said> Drawing up a chair, he sat down opposite her,
          and tried to console her by <said aloud="true" direct="false" who="Fridolin"
            listener="Marianne">saying that her father must have suffered very little at the last.
            He then
            asked if any of her relatives had been notified.</said> <said aloud="true" direct="false"
            who="Marianne" listener="Fridolin">Yes, she said, the housekeeper had
            already gone to tell her uncle, and very likely Doctor Roediger would soon appear.</said> <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Marianne" listener="Fridolin">"My
            fiance,"</said> she added, and did not look him straight in the eye. <rs ref="#Fridolin">
          Fridolin</rs> simply nodded. During the year he had met <rs ref="#Roediger">Doctor
            Roediger</rs> two or three times in the Councilor's house. The pale young man—an
          instructor in History at the University of Vienna—was of an unusually slender build with a
          short, blond beard and spectacles, and had made quite a good impression upon him, without,
          however, arousing his interest beyond that. <rs ref="#Marianne">Marianne</rs> would
          certainly look better, he thought to himself, if she were his mistress. Her hair would be
          less dry, her lips would be fuller and redder. <said aloud="false" direct="false"
            who="Fridolin">I wonder how
            old she is, he reflected. The first time I attended the Councilor, three or four years
          ago, she was twentv-three. At that time her mother was still living and she was more
          cheerful than now. She even took singing lessons for a while. So she is going to marry
            this instructor! I wonder why? She surely isn't in love with him, and he isn't likely to
          have much money either. What kind of a marriage will it turn out to be? Probably like a
          thousand others. But it's none of my business. It's quite possible that I shall never see
          her again, since there's nothing more for me to do here. Well, many others that I cared
            for have gone the same way.</said> As these thoughts passed through his mind, <rs
            ref="#Marianne">Marianne</rs> began to speak of her father—with fervor—as if his death
          had suddenly made him a more remarkable person. <said aloud="false" direct="false"
            who="Fridolin">Then he was really only fifty-four years old? Well, of course, he had had
          so many worries and disappointments—his wife always ill—and his son such a grief! What,
            she had a brother? Certainly, she had once told the doctor about him. </said>Her brother
          was now living somewhere abroad. A picture that he had painted when he was fifteen was
          hanging over there in <rs ref="#Marianne">Marianne</rs>'s room. It represented an officer
          galloping down a hill. Her father had always pretended not to see it although it wasn't
          bad. Oh yes, if he'd had a chance her brother might have made something of himself. <said
            aloud="false" direct="false"
            who="Fridolin">How
            excitedly she speaks</said>, <rs ref="#Fridolin">
            Fridolin</rs> thought, <said aloud="false" direct="false"
            who="Fridolin">and how bright her eyes are! Is it fever? Quite possibly. She's
            grown much thinner. Probably has tuberculosis.</said> She kept up her stream of talk,
          but it seemed to him that she didn't quite know what she was saying. It was twelve years
          since her brother had left home. In fact, she had been a child when he disappeared. They
          had last heard from him four or five years ago, at Christmas, from a small city in Italy.
          Strange to say, she had forgotten the name. She continued like this for a while, almost
          incoherently. Suddenly she stopped and sat there silently, her head resting in her hands. <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> was tired and even more bored. He was anxiously waiting
          for some one to come, her relatives, or her fiance. The silence in the room was
          oppressive. It seemed to him that the dead man joined in the silence, deliberately and
          with malicious joy. With a side glance at the corpse, he said: <said aloud="true"
            direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Marianne">At any rate, Fraulein <rs
              ref="#Marianne">Marianne</rs>, as things are now, it is fortunate that you won't have
          to stay in this house very much longer."</said> And when she raised her head a little,
          without, however, looking at <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs>, he continued: <said aloud="true" direct="true"
            who="Fridolin" listener="Marianne">"I suppose your fiance will soon get a
            professorship. The chances for promotion are more favorable in the Faculty of Philosophy
          than with us in Medicine."</said> He was thinking that, years ago, he also had aspired to
          an academic career, but because he wanted a comfortable income, he had finally decided to
          practice medicine. Suddenly he felt that compared with this noble <rs ref="#Roediger">Doctor
          Roediger</rs>, he was the inferior. <said aloud="true" direct="true" who="Marianne"
            listener="Fridolin">We shall move soon,"</said> <rs ref="#Marianne">Marianne</rs>
          listlessly, <said aloud="true" direct="true" who="Marianne" listener="Fridolin">"he has a
          post at the University of Gottingen."</said> <said aloud="true" direct="true"
            who="Fridolin" listener="Marianne">"Oh,"</said> said <rs ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs>,
          and was about to congratulate her but it seemed rather out of place at the moment. He
          glanced at the closed window, and without asking for permission but availing himself of
          his privilege as a doctor, he opened both casements and let some air in. It had become
          even warmer and more spring-like, and the breeze seemed to bring with it a slight
          fragrance of the distant awakening woods. When he turned back into the room, he saw <rs
            ref="#Marianne">Marianne</rs>'s eyes fixed upon him with a questioning look. He moved
          nearer to her and said: <said aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin"
            listener="Marianne">"I hope the fresh air will be good for you. It has become quite
            warm, and last night"</said>—he was about to say: we drove home from the masquerade in a
          snowstorm, but he quickly changed the sentence and continued: <said aloud="true"
            direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Marianne">"Last night the snow was
            still lying on the streets a foot and a half deep."</said> She hardly heard what he
          said. Her eyes became moist, large tears streamed down her cheeks and again she buried her
          face in her hands. In spite of himself, he placed his hand on her head, caressing it. He
          could feel her body beginning to tremble, and her sobs which were at first very quiet,
          gradually became louder and finally quite unrestrained. All at once she slipped down from
          her chair and lay at <rs ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs>'s feet, clasping his knees with her
          arms and pressing her face against them. Then she looked up to him with large eyes, wild
          with grief, and whispered ardently: <said aloud="true" direct="true" who="Marianne"
            listener="Fridolin">"I don't want to leave here. Even if you never return, if I
            am never to see you again, I want, at least, to live near you."</said> He was touched
          rather than surprised, for he had always known that she either was, or imagined herself to
          be, in love with him. <said aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Marianne">"Please—get
          up, <rs ref="#Marianne">Marianne</rs>,"</said> he said softly and bending down he gently
          raised her. Of course, she is hysterical, he remarked to himself and he glanced at her
          dead father. <said aloud="false" direct="false" who="Fridolin">I wonder if he hears
          everything</said>, he thought. Perhaps he isn't really dead. Perhaps everyone in the first
          hours after passing away, is only in a coma. He put his arms about her in a very
          hesitating embrace, and almost against his will he kissed her on the forehead, an act that
          somehow seemed rather ridiculous. He had a fleeting recollection of reading a novel years
          ago in which a young man, still almost a boy, had been seduced, in fact, practically
          raped, by the friend of his mother at the latter's deathbed. At the same time he thought
          of his wife, without knowing why, and he was conscious of some bitterness and a vague
          animosity against the man with the yellow hand-bag on the hotel stairs in Denmark. He held <rs
            ref="#Marianne">Marianne</rs> closer, but without the slightest emotion. The sight of
          her lustreless, dry hair, the indefinite, sweetish scent of her unaired dress gave him a
          slight feeling of revulsion. The bell outside rang again, and feeling he was released, he
          hastily kissed <rs ref="#Marianne">
            Marianne</rs>'s hand, as if in gratitude, and went to open the door. <rs ref="#Roediger">Doctor
          Roediger</rs> stood there, in a dark gray top-coat, an umbrella in his hand and a serious
          face, appropriate to the occasion. The two men greeted each other much more cordially than
          was called for by their actual state of acquaintance. Then they stepped into the room.
          After an embarrassed look at the deceased, <rs ref="#Roediger">Roediger</rs> expressed his
          sympathy to <rs
            ref="#Marianne">Marianne</rs>, while <rs ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> went into the
          adjoining room to write out the official death certificate. He turned up the gas-light
          over the desk and his eyes fell upon the picture of the whiteuniformed officer, galloping
          down hill, with drawn sabre, to meet an invisible enemy. It hung in a narrow frame of dull
          gold and rather resembled a modest chromo-lithograph. With his death-certificate filled
          out, <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> returned to the room where the engaged couple sat, hand in
          hand, by the bed of the dead Councilor. Again the door-bell rang and Doctor Roediger rose
          to answer it. While he was gone, <rs ref="#Marianne">Marianne</rs>, with her eyes on the
          floor, said, almost inaudibly: <said aloud="true" direct="true" who="Marianne"
            listener="Fridolin">"I love you,"</said>and <rs ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> answered
          by <said aloud="true" direct="false" who="Fridolin" listener="Marianne">pronouncing her
          name tenderly</said>. Then <rs ref="#Roediger">Roediger</rs> came back with an elderly
          couple, <rs
            ref="#Marianne">Marianne</rs>'s uncle and aunt, and a few words, appropriate to the
          occasion, were exchanged, with the usual embarrassment in the presence of one who has just
          died. The little room suddenly seemed crowded with mourners. <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> felt superfluous, took his leave and was escorted to the
          door by Roediger who said a few words of gratitude and expressed the hope of seeing him
          soon again. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" n="3">
        <head>3.</head>
        <p>WHEN <rs ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> stood on the street in front of the house, he
          looked up at the window which he himself had opened a little while before. The casements
          were swaying slightly in the wind of early spring, and the people who remained behind them
          up there, the living as well as the dead, all seemed unreal and phantomlike. He felt as if
          he had escaped from something, not so much from an adventure, but rather from a melancholy
          spell the power of which he was trying to break. He felt strangely disinclined to go home.
          The snow in the streets had melted, except where little heaps of dirty white had been
          piled up on either side of the curb. The gas-flame in the street lamps flickered and a
          nearby church bell struck eleven. <rs ref="#Fridolin">
            Fridolin</rs> decided that before going to bed, he would spend a half hour in a quiet
          nook of a cafe near his residence. As he walked through Rathaus Park he noticed here and
          there on benches standing in the shadow, that couples were sitting, clasped together, just
          as if Spring had actually arrived and no danger were lurking in the deceptive, warm air. A
          tramp in tattered clothes was lying full length on a bench with his hat over his face. <said
            aloud="false" direct="false" who="Fridolin">Suppose I wake him and give him some money
          for a night's lodging </said>, <rs ref="#Fridolin">
            Fridolin</rs> thought. <said
            aloud="false" direct="false" who="Fridolin">But what good would that do? Then I would
          have to provide for the
            next night, too, or there'd be no sense in it, and in the end I might be suspected of
          having criminal relations with him.</said> He quickened his steps to escape as rapidly as
          possible from all responsibility and temptation. <said
            aloud="false" direct="false" who="Fridolin">And why only this one?</said> he asked
          himself. There are thousands of such poor devils in Vienna alone. It's manifestly
          impossible to help all of them or to worry about all the poor wretches! He was reminded of
          the dead man he had just left, and shuddered; in fact, he felt slightly nauseated at the
          thought that decay and decomposition, according to eternal laws, had already begun their
          work in the lean body under the brown flannel blanket. He was glad that he was still
          alive, and in all probability these ugly things were still far removed from him. He was,
          in fact, still in the prime of youth, he had a charming and lovable wife and could have
          several women in addition, if he happened to want them, although, to be sure, such affairs
          required more leisure than was his. He then remembered that he would have to be in his
          ward at the hospital at eight in the morning, visit his private patients from eleven to
          one, keep office hours from three to five, and that even in the evening he had several
          appointments to visit patients. Well, he hoped that it would be some time before he would
          again be called out so late at night. As he crossed Rathaus Square, which had a dull gleam
          like a brownish pond, and turned homeward, he heard the muffled sound of marching steps in
          the distance. Then he saw, still quite far away, a small group of fraternity students, six
          or eight in number, turning a corner and coming towards him. When the light of a street
          lamp fell upon them he thought he recognized them, with their blue caps, as members of the
          Alemannia, for although he had never belonged to a fraternity, he had fought a few sabre
          duels in his time. In thinking of his student days he was reminded again of the <rs
            ref="#2W">red
            dominoes</rs> who had lured him into a box at the ball the night before and then had so
          shamefully deserted him. The students were quite near now; they were laughing and talking
          loudly. Perhaps one or two of them were from the hospital? But it was impossible to see
          their faces plainly because of the dim light, and he had to stay quite close to the houses
          so as not to collide with them. Now they had passed. Only the one in the rear, a tall
          fellow with open overcoat and a bandage over his left eye, seemed to lag behind, and
          deliberately bumped into him with his raised elbow. It couldn't have been mere chance. <said
            aloud="false" direct="false" who="Fridolin">What's got into that fellow?</said> <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> thought, and involuntarily he stopped. The other took two
          more steps and turned. They looked at each other for a moment with only a short distance
          separating them. Suddenly <rs ref="#Fridolin">
            Fridolin</rs> turned around again and went on. He heard a short laugh behind him and he
          longed to challenge the fellow, but he felt his heart beating strangely, just as it had on
          a previous occasion, twelve or fourteen years before. There had been an unusually loud
          knock on his door while he had had with him a certain charming young creature who was
          never tired of prattling about her jealous fiance. As a matter of fact, it was only the
          postman who had knocked in such a threatening manner. And now he felt his heart beating
          just as it had at that time. <said
            aloud="false" direct="false" who="Fridolin">What's the meaning of this?</said> he asked
          himself, and he noticed that his knees were shaking a little. <said
            aloud="false" direct="false" who="Fridolin">Am I a coward? Oh! nonsense</said>, he
          reassured himself. <said
            aloud="false" direct="false" who="Fridolin">Why should I go and face a drunken student,
          I, a man of thirty-five, a practising
            physician, a married man and father of a child? Formal challenge! Seconds! A duel! And
          perhaps because of such a silly encounter receive a cut in my arm and be unable to perform
          my professional duties?—Or lose an eye?—Or even get blood-poisoning?—And in a week perhaps
          be in the same position as the man in Schreyvogel Strasse under the brown flannel blanket?
          Coward—?</said> He had fought three sabre duels, and had even been ready to fight a duel
          with pistols, and it wasn't at his request that the matter had been called off. And what
          about his profession! There were dangers lurking everywhere and at all times—except that
          one usually forgets about them. Why, how long ago was it that that child with diphtheria
          had coughed in his face? Only three or four days, that's all. After all, that was much
          more dangerous than a little fencing match with sabres, and he hadn't given it a second
          thought. Well, if he ever met that fellow again, the affair could still be straightened
          out. He was by no means bound by the code of honor to take a silly encounter with a
          student seriously when on an errand of mercy, to or from a patient. But if, for instance,
          he should meet the young Dane with whom <rs
            ref="#Albertina">Albertina</rs>— oh, nonsense, what was he thinking of? Well, after all,
          it was just as bad as if she had been his mistress. Even worse. Yes, just let that fellow
          cross his path! What a joy it would be to face him somewhere in a clearing in the woods
          and aim a pistol at his forehead with its smoothly combed blond hair. He suddenly
          discovered that he had passed his destination. He was in a narrow street in which only a
          few doubtful-looking women were strolling about in a pitiful attempt to bag their game. <said
            aloud="false" direct="false" who="Fridolin">It's phantomlike</said>, he thought. And in
          retrospect the students, too, with their blue caps, suddenly seemed unreal. The same was
          true of <rs ref="#Marianne">Marianne</rs>, her fiance, her uncle and aunt, all of whom he
          pictured standing hand in hand around the deathbed of the old <rs ref="councilor">
          Councilor</rs>. <rs
            ref="#Albertina">Albertina</rs>, too, whom he could see in his mind's eye soundly
          sleeping, her arms folded under her head—even his child lying in the narrow white brass
          bed, rolled up in a heap, and the red-cheeked governess with the mole on her left
          temple—all of them seemed to belong to another world. Although this idea made him shudder
          a bit, it also reassured him, for it seemed to free him from all responsibility, and to
          loosen all the bonds of human relationship. <rs ref="#Mizzi">One of the girls</rs>
          wandering about stopped him. She was still a young and pretty little thing, very pale with
          red-painted lips. <said
            aloud="false" direct="false" who="Fridolin">She also
            might lead to a fatal end, only not as quickly</said>, he thought. <said
            aloud="false" direct="false" who="Fridolin">Is this cowardice too? I
            suppose really it is</said>. He heard her steps and then her voice behind him. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Mizzi" listener="Fridolin">Won't you come
            with me, doctor?"</said> He turned around involuntarily. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Mizzi">"How do you know who I am?"</said>
          he asked. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Mizzi" listener="Fridolin">"Why, I don't know you,"</said>
          she said, <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Mizzi" listener="Fridolin">"but here in this part of
            town they're all doctors, aren't they?"</said> He had had no relations with a woman of
          this sort since he had been a student at the Gymnasium. Was the attraction this girl had
          for him a sign that he was suddenly reverting to adolescence? He recalled a casual
          acquaintance, a smart young man, who was supposed to be extremely successful with women.
          Once while <rs ref="#Fridolin">
            Fridolin</rs> was a student he had been sitting with him in an all-night cafe, after a
          ball. When the young man proposed to leave with one of the regular girls of the place, <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> looked at him in surprise. Thereupon he answered: <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Mizzi">"After
            all, it's the most convenient way— and they aren't by any means the worst." "What's your
          name?"</said> <rs ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> asked the girl. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Mizzi" listener="Fridolin">"Well, what do you think?
          Mizzi,
            of course."</said> She unlocked the house-door, stepped into the hallway and waited for <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> to follow her. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Mizzi" listener="Fridolin">"Come on,"</said> she said
          when he hesitated. He stepped in beside her, the door closed behind him, she locked it,
          lit a wax candle and went ahead, lighting the way.<said
            aloud="false" direct="false" who="Fridolin">—Am I mad?</said> he asked himself. Of
          course I shall have nothing to do with her. An oil-lamp was burning in her room, and she
          turned it up. It was a fairly pleasant place and neatly kept. At any rate, it smelled
          fresher than <rs ref="#Marianne">
            Marianne</rs>'s home, for instance. But then, of course, no old man had been lying ill
          there for months. <rs ref="#Mizzi">The girl</rs> smiled, and without forwardness
          approached <rs ref="#Fridolin">
            Fridolin</rs> who gently kept her at a distance. She pointed to a rocking-chair into
          which he was glad to drop. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Mizzi" listener="Fridolin">"You must be very tired,"</said>
          she remarked. He nodded. Undressing without haste, she continued: <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Mizzi" listener="Fridolin">"Well, no wonder, with all
            the things a man like you has to do in
            the course of a day. We have an easier time of it."</said> He noticed that her lips were
          not painted, as he had thought, but were a natural red, and he complimented her on that. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Mizzi" listener="Fridolin">"But
            why should I rouge?" she inquired. "How old do you think I am?"</said> <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Mizzi">"Twenty?"</said> <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> ventured. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Mizzi" listener="Fridolin">"Seventeen,"</said> she said,
          and sat on his lap, putting her arms around his neck like a child. <said
            aloud="false" direct="false" who="Fridolin">Who in the world would suspect that I'm
            here in this room at this moment?</said> <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> thought. <said
            aloud="false" direct="false" who="Fridolin">I'd never have thought it possible an hour
            or
            even ten minutes ago. And— why? Why am I here?</said> Her lips were seeking his, but he
          drew back his head. She looked at him with sad surprise and slipped down from his lap. He
          was sorry, for he had felt much comforting tenderness in her embrace. She took a red
          dressing-gown which was hanging over the foot of the open bed, slipped into it and folded
          her arms over her breast so that her entire body was concealed. <said aloud="true"
            direct="true" who="Mizzi" listener="Fridolin">"Does this suit you better?"</said> she
          asked without mockery, almost timidly, as though making an effort to understand him. He
          hardly knew what to answer. <said aloud="true"
            direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Mizzi">"You're right,"</said> he said. <said
            aloud="true"
            direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Mizzi">"I am really tired, and I find it
            very pleasant sitting here in the rocking-chair and simply listening to you. You have
          such
            a nice gentle voice. Just talk to me."</said> She sat down on the couch and shook her
          head. <said aloud="true"
            direct="true" who="Mizzi" listener="Fridolin">"You're simply afraid,"</said> she said
          softly —and then to herself in a barely audible voice: <said aloud="true"
            direct="true" who="Mizzi">"It's too bad."</said> These last words made the blood race
          through his veins. He walked over to her, longing to touch her, and declared that he
          trusted her implicitly and saying so he spoke the truth. He put his arms around her and
          wooed her like a sweetheart, like a beloved woman, but she resisted, until he felt ashamed
          and finally gave it up. She explained: <said aloud="true"
            direct="true" who="Mizzi" listener="Fridolin">"You never can tell, some time or other
          it's bound to get out.
            It's quite right of you to be afraid. If something should happen, you would curse me."</said>
          She was so positive in refusing the banknotes which he offered her that he did not insist.
          She put a little blue woolen shawl about her shoulders, lit a candle to light him
          downstairs, went down with him and unlocked the door. <said aloud="true"
            direct="true" who="Mizzi" listener="Fridolin">"I'm not going out any more tonight,"</said>she
          said. He took her hand and involuntarily kissed it. She looked up to him astonished,
          almost frightened. Then she laughed, embarrassed and happy. <said aloud="true"
            direct="true" who="Mizzi" listener="Fridolin">"Just as if I were a young lady,"</said>
          she said. The door closed behind <rs ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> and he quickly made a
          mental note of the street number, so as to be able to send the poor little thing some wine
          and cakes the following day. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="chapter" n="4">
        <head>4.</head>
        <p> MEANWHILE it had become even milder outside. A fragrance from dewy meadows and distant
          mountains drifted with the gentle breezes into the narrow street. <said aloud="false"
            direct="false" who="Fridolin">Where shall I go now? </said><rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> asked himself, as though it weren't the obvious thing to
          go home to bed. But he couldn't persuade himself to do so. He felt homeless, an outcast,
          since his annoying meeting with the students ... or was it since <rs ref="#Marianne">
          Marianne</rs>'s confession? No, it was longer than that—ever since this evening's
          conversation with <rs ref="#Albertina">Albertina</rs> he was moving farther and farther
          away from his everyday existence into some strange and distant world. He wandered about
          aimlessly through the dark streets, letting the breeze blow through his hair. Finally, he
          turned resolutely into a third-rate coffee-house. The place was dimly lighted and not
          especially large, but it had an old-fashioned, cozy air about it, and was almost empty at
          this late hour. Three men were playing cards in a corner. The waiter who had been watching
          them helped <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> take off his fur coat, took his order and placed
          illustrated journals and evening papers on his table. <rs ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs>
          felt slightly more secure and began to look through the papers. His eyes were arrested
          here and there by some news-item. In some Bohemian city, street signs with German names
          had been torn down. There was a conference in Constantinople in which Lord Cranford took
          part about constructing a railway in Asia Minor. The firm Benies &amp; Weingruber had gone
          into bankruptcy. The prostitute Anna Tiger, in a fit of jealousy, had attempted to throw
          vitriol on her friend, Hermine Drobizky. An Ash Wednesday fishdinner was being given that
          evening in Sophia Hall. Marie B., a young girl residing at No. 28 Schonbrunn Strasse, had
          poisoned herself with mercuric chloride.—Prosaically commonplace as they were, all these
          facts, the insignificant as well as the sad, had a sobering and reassuring effect on <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs>. He felt sorry for the young girl, Marie B. How stupid to
          take mercuric chloride! At this very moment, while he was sitting snugly in the cafe,
          while <rs
            ref="#Albertina">Albertina</rs> was calmly sleeping, and the <rs ref="#councilor">
          Councilor</rs>had passed beyond all human suffering, Marie B., No. 28 Schonbrunn Strasse,
          was writhing in incredible pain. He looked up from his paper and encountered the gaze of a
          man seated opposite. <said aloud="false" direct="false" who="Fridolin">Was it possible? <rs
              ref="#Nachtigall">Nachtigall</rs>—?</said> The latter had already recognized him,
          threw up his hands in pleased surprise and joined him at his table. He was still a young
          man, tall, rather broad, and none too thin. His long, blond, slightly curly hair had a
          touch of gray in it, and his moustache drooped in Polish fashion. He was wearing an open
          gray top-coat, underneath which were visible a greasy dress-suit, a crumpled shirt with
          three false diamond studs, a crinkled collar and a dangling, white silk tie. His eyelids
          were inflamed, as if from many sleepless nights, but his blue eyes gleamed brightly. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Nachtigall">You here in Vienna, <rs
              ref="#Nachtigall">Nachtigall</rs>?"</said> exclaimed <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs>. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Nachtigall" listener="Fridolin">"Didn't you know?"</said>
          said <rs ref="#Nachtigall">Nachtigall</rs> with a soft, Polish accent and a slightly
          Jewish twang. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Nachtigall" listener="Fridolin">"How could you miss it,
          and me so
            famous?"</said> He laughed loudly and good-naturedly, and sat down opposite <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs>. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Nachtigall">"What,"</said> asked <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs>, <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Nachtigall">"have
            you been appointed Professor of Surgery without my hearing of it?"</said> <rs
            ref="#Nachtigall">
            Nachtigall</rs> laughed still louder. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Nachtigall" listener="Fridolin">"Didn't you hear me just
          now, just a minute ago?"</said>
          <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Nachtigall">"What do you mean—hear
          you?—Why, of course."</said> Suddenly it occurred to him that someone had been playing the
          piano when he entered; in fact, he had heard music coming from some basement as he
          approached the cafe. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Nachtigall">"So that was you
          playing?"</said> he exclaimed. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Nachtigall" listener="Fridolin">"It was,"</said> <rs
            ref="#Nachtigall">Nachtigall</rs> said, laughing. <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> nodded. Why, of course—the strangely vigorous touch, the
          peculiar, but euphonious bass chords had at once seemed familiar to him. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Nachtigall">"Are you devoting
          yourself entirely to it?"</said> he asked. He remembered that <rs ref="#Nachtigall">
          Nachtigall</rs> had definitely given up the study of medicine after his second preliminary
          examination in zoology, which he had passed although he was seven years late in taking it.
          Since then he had been hanging around the hospital, the dissecting room, the laboratories
          and classrooms for some time afterwards. With his blond artist's head, his crinkled
          collar, his dangling tie that had once been white, he had been a striking and, in the
          humorous sense, popular figure. He had been much liked, not only by his fellow-students,
          but also by many professors. The son of a Jewish gin-shop owner in a small Polish town, he
          had left home early and had come to Vienna to study medicine. The trifling sums he
          received from his parents had from the very-beginning been scarcely worth mention and were
          soon discontinued. However, this didn't prevent his appearing in the Riedhof Hotel at the
          table reserved for medical students where <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> was a regular guest. At intervals, one after another of
          his more well-todo fellow-students would pay his bill. He sometimes, also, was given
          clothes, which he accepted gladly and without false pride. He had already learned to play
          in his home town from a pianist stranded there, and while he was a medical student in
          Vienna he had studied at the Conservatory where he was considered a talented musician of
          great promise. But here, too, he was neither serious nor diligent enough to develop his
          art systematically. He soon became entirely content with the impression he made on his
          acquaintances, or rather with the pleasure he gave them by his playing. For a while he had
          a position as pianist in a suburban dancing-school. Fellow-students and table-companions
          tried to introduce him into fashionable houses in the same capacity, but on such occasions
          he would play only what suited him and as long as he chose. His conversations with the
          young girls present were not always harmless, and he drank more than he could carry. Once,
          playing for a dance in the house of a wealthy banker, he embarrassed several couples with
          flattering but improper remarks, and ended up by playing a wild cancan and singing a
          risque song with his powerful, bass voice. The host gave him a severe calling down, but <rs
            ref="#Nachtigall">Nachtigall</rs>, blissfully hilarious, got up and embraced him. The
          latter was furious and, although himself a Jew, hurled a common insult at him. <rs
            ref="#Nachtigall">Nachtigall</rs> at once retaliated with a powerful box on his ears,
          and this definitely concluded his career in the fashionable houses of the city. He behaved
          better, on the whole, in more intimate circles, although sometimes when the hour was late,
          he had to be put out of the place by force. But the following morning all was forgiven and
          forgotten. One day, long after his friends had graduated, he disappeared from the city
          without a word. For a few months he sent post cards from various Russian and Polish
          cities, and once <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs>, who was one of <rs ref="#Nachtigall">Nachtigall</rs>'s
          favorites, was reminded of his existence not only by a card, but by a request for a
          moderate sum of money, without explanation. <rs ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> sent it at
          once, but never received a word of thanks or any other sign of life from <rs
            ref="#Nachtigall">Nachtigall</rs>. At this moment, however, eight years later, at a
          quarter to one in the morning, <rs ref="#Nachtigall">Nachtigall</rs> insisted on paying
          his debt, and took the exact amount in bank-notes from a rather shabby pocket-book. As the
          latter was fairly well filled, <rs ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> accepted the repayment
          with a good conscience. <said aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin"
            listener="Nachtigall">Are you getting along well,"</said> he asked with a smile, in
          order to make sure. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Nachtigall" listener="Fridolin">"I can't complain,"</said>
          replied <rs ref="#Nachtigall">Nachtigall</rs>. Placing his hand on <rs ref="#Fridolin">
          Fridolin</rs>'s arm, he continued: <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Nachtigall" listener="Fridolin">"But tell me, why are
            you
            here so late at night?"</said> <rs ref="#Fridolin">
            Fridolin</rs> explained that <said aloud="true" direct="false" who="Fridolin"
            listener="Nachtigall">he had needed a cup of coffee after visiting a patient,
            although he didn't say, without quite knowing why, that he hadn't found his patient
          alive.
            Then he talked in very general terms of his duties at the hospital and his private
          practice, and mentioned that he was happily married, and the father of a six-year old
            girl.</said> <rs ref="#Nachtigall">Nachtigall</rs> in his turn, <said aloud="true"
            direct="false" who="Nachtigall" listener="Fridolin">explained that he had spent the time
          as a pianist in every possible sort of Polish, Roumanian, Serbian and Bulgarian city and
          town, just as <rs
              ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> had surmised. He had a wife and four children living in
          Lemberg, and he laughed heartily, as though it were unusually jolly to have four children,
          all of them living in Lemberg, and all by one and the same woman. He had been back in
          Vienna since the preceding fall. The vaudeville company he had been with had suddenly gone
          to pieces. He was now playing anywhere and everywhere, anything that happened to come
          along, sometimes in two or three different houses the same night. For example, down there
          in that basement—not at all a fashionable place, as he remarked, really a sort of bowling
          alley, and with very doubtful patrons. . . .</said><said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Nachtigall" listener="Fridolin"> "But if you have to
          provide for four children
            and a wife in Lemberg"—he laughed again, though not quite as gaily as before, and added:
          "But sometimes I am privately engaged."</said> Noticing a reminiscent smile on <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs>'s face, he continued: <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Nachtigall" listener="Fridolin">"Not just in the houses
          of bankers
            and such, but in all kinds of circles, even larger ones, both public and secret."</said>
          <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Nachtigall">"Secret?</said>" <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> asked. <rs ref="#Nachtigall">Nachtigall</rs> looked
          straight before him with a gloomy and crafty air, and said: <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Nachtigall" listener="Fridolin">"They will be calling
            for me
            again in a minute."</said> <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Nachtigall">"What, are you playing
          somewhere else tonight?"</said> <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Nachtigall" listener="Fridolin">"Yes, they only begin
          there at two."</said> <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Nachtigall">"It must be an unusually
          smart place."</said> <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Nachtigall" listener="Fridolin">"Yes and no,"</said>
          said <rs
            ref="#Nachtigall">Nachtigall</rs>, laughing, but he became serious again at once. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Nachtigall">"Yes
            and no?"</said> queried <rs ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs>, curiously. <rs
            ref="#Nachtigall">
            Nachtigall</rs> bent across the table. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Nachtigall" listener="Fridolin">"I'm playing tonight in
            a private house, but I
            don't know whose it is."</said> <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Nachtigall">"Then you're playing
          there for the first time?"</said> <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">
            Fridolin</rs> asked with increasing interest. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Nachtigall" listener="Fridolin">"No, it's the third
            time, but it will
            probably be a different house again."</said> <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Nachtigall">"I don't understand."</said> <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Nachtigall" listener="Fridolin">"Neither do I,"</said>
          said <rs
            ref="#Nachtigall">Nachtigall</rs>, laughing, <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Nachtigall" listener="Fridolin">"but you'd better not
            ask any more."</said> <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Nachtigall">"Oh, I
            see,"</said> remarked <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs>. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Nachtigall" listener="Fridolin">"No, you're wrong. It's
          not what you think. I've seen a
            great deal in my time. It's unbelievable what one sees in such small towns, especially
            in
            Roumania, but here . . ."</said> He drew back the yellow curtain from the window, looked
          out on the street and said as if to himself: <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Nachtigall" listener="Fridolin">"Not here yet."</said>
          Then he turned to <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> and explained: <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Nachtigall" listener="Fridolin">"I mean the carriage.
          There's always a
            carriage to call for me, a different one each time."</said> <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Nachtigall">"You're making me very
          curious, <rs
              ref="#Nachtigall">Nachtigall</rs>,"</said> <rs ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> assured
          him. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Nachtigall" listener="Fridolin">"Listen to me,"</said>
          said <rs ref="#Nachtigall">Nachtigall</rs> after a slight pause. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Nachtigall" listener="Fridolin">"I'd like
            to be able to arrange it—'but how can I do it—"</said> Suddenly he burst out: <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Nachtigall" listener="Fridolin">"Have you got
            plenty of nerve?"</said> <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Nachtigall">"That's a strange
          question,"</said> said <rs
            ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</rs> in the tone of an offended fraternity student. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Nachtigall" listener="Fridolin">"I don't
            mean that."</said> <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Nachtigall">"Well, what do you
          mean?—Why does one need so much courage for this affair?
            What can possibly happen?"</said> He gave a short and contemptuous laugh. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Nachtigall" listener="Fridolin">"Nothing can happen to
          me. At best this would be the last time—but perhaps that may be the case anyhow."</said>
          He stopped and looked out again through the crevice in the curtain. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Nachtigall">"Well, then where's the
          difficulty?"</said> <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Nachtigall" listener="Fridolin">"What did you say?"</said>
          asked <rs ref="#Nachtigall">Nachtigall</rs>, as if coming out of a dream. <said
            aloud="true" direct="true" who="Fridolin" listener="Nachtigall">"Tell me the rest of the
          story, now that you've started. A secret party?
            Closed affair? Nothing but invited guests?"</said>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>