<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Dream Story</title>
        <title type="alt">Traumnovelle</title>
        <title type="alt">Rhapsody: A Dream Novel</title>
        <editor role="Translator">Otto P. Schinnerer</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent>
        <measure unit="pages" quantity="143">143 pages</measure>
      </extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Green Integer</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Los Angeles</pubPlace>
        <idno type="ISBN-10">1931243484</idno>
        <idno type="ISBN-13">9781931243483</idno>
        <date>2003</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title level="s">Masterworks of fiction</title>
        <biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note><!-- notes on other aspects of the resource --></note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p><!-- information about the source from which the resource was derived  --></p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>

  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1" type="chapter">


        <p>
          But now that the day's work was done— the child had gone to bed and no disturbance was
          likely—the
          shadowy forms of the masquerade, the melancholy stranger and the red dominoes, rose again
          into
          reality. And all at once those insignificant events were imbued, magically and painfully,
          with the
          deceptive glow of neglected opportunities. Harmless but probing questions, and sly,
          ambiguous answers
          were exchanged. Neither failed to notice that the other was not absolutely honest, and so
          they became
          slightly vindictive. They exaggerated the degree of attraction that their unknown partners
          at the ball had
          exerted upon them while each made fun of the other's tendencies to jealousy and denied his
          own. Soon,
          their light conversation about the trifling matters of the night before changed into a
          more serious
          discussion of those hidden, scarcely suspected wishes, which can produce dangerous
          whirlpools even in
          the serenest and purest soul. They spoke of those mysterious regions of which they were
          hardly
          conscious but toward which the incomprehensible wind of fate might some day drive them,
          even if only
          in their dreams. For though they were united in thought and feeling, they knew that the
          preceding day
          had not been the first time that the spirit of adventure, freedom and danger had beckoned
          them.
          Uneasy, and tormenting themselves, each sought with disingenuous curiosity to draw out
          confessions
          from the other. Anxiously, they searched within themselves for some indifferent fact, or
          trifling
          experience, which might express the inexpressible, and the honest confession of which
          might relieve
          them of the strain and the suspicion which were becoming unbearable.</p>

        <p> Whether <persName ref="#Albertina">Albertina</persName> was more impatient, more honest
          or more kind-hearted of the two, it was she who first summoned the courage for a frank
          confession. She asked <persName ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</persName> in a rather uncertain
          voice whether he remembered the young man who—last summer at the seashore in <placeName
            ref="#Denmark">Denmark</placeName>—had been sitting one evening with two other officers
          at an adjoining table. He had received a telegram during dinner, whereupon he had hastily
          said "good-bye" to his friends.</p>

        <p>
          <persName ref="Fridolin">Fridolin</persName> nodded. "What about him?" he asked.
        </p>
=======

    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">
          Dream Stories
        </title>
        <title type="alt">
          Traumnovelle
        </title>
        <title type="alt">
          Rhapsody: A Dream Novel
        </title>
        <editor role="Translator">
          Otto P. Schinnerer
        </editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <extent>
        <measure unit="pages" quantity="143">143 pages</measure>
      </extent>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Green Integer</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Los Angeles</pubPlace>
        <idno type="ISBN-10">1931243484</idno>
        <idno type="ISBN-13">9781931243483</idno>
        <date>2003</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <p>
          Masterworks of fiction
        </p>
        <biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
      </seriesStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>
          <!-- notes on other aspects of the resource -->
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>
          <!-- information about the source from which
                                the resource was derived  -->
        </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <particDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <person>
            <persName>Fridolin</persName>
          </person>
          <person>
            <persName>Albertina</persName>
          </person>
        </listPerson>
      </particDesc>
    </profileDesc>

  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart>RHAPSODY A DREAM NOVEL</titlePart>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Arthur Schnitzler</docAuthor> Translated from the German by OTTO P.
            SCHINNERER </byline>
        </docTitle>
      </titlePage>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="chapter" n="1">
        <head>1.</head>
        <p>
          <quote>"TWENTY-FOUR brown-skinned slaves rowed the splendid galley which was to bring
          Prince Amgiad to the palace of the caliph. The Prince, wrapped in his purple cloak, lay
          alone on the deck
            under the dark-blue, starry sky, and his gaze—"</quote><lb /> So far the little girl had
          read aloud.Then, suddenly, her eyelids drooped. Her parents looked at each other and
          smiled. <persName ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</persName> bent down, kissed her blond hair and closed
          the book which was lying on the untidy table. The child looked up as if caught at some
          mischief.<lb />
          
          
          
            <said aloud="true" direct="true">"It's nine o'clock,"</said> her father
          said, <said aloud="true" direct="true">"and time you were in bed."</said> <persName ref="#Albertina">Albertina</persName>also bent over her, and as her hand met her husband's
          on the beloved forehead, they looked at each other with a tender smile not meant for the
          child. The governess entered and asked the little girl to say good-night. She got up
          obediently, kissed her father and mother and walked out quietly hand in hand with the
          young woman. <persName ref="#Fridolin">Fridolin</persName> and <persName ref="#Albertina">Albertina</persName>,
          left alone under the reddish glow of the hanging-lamp, continued the conversation they had
          begun before supper. </p>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>